<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daina Chiba</title>
    <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/daina-chiba/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/daina-chiba/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Daina Chiba</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dainachiba.github.io/media/icon_hu2e8632b74444b790220bb01d3e17bdf2_10117_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Daina Chiba</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/daina-chiba/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gender Gap in Peace and Conflict Journals, 2000-2024</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/genderpeaceconflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/genderpeaceconflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While the issue of gender representation has gained increasing recognition across various academic disciplines, existing knowledge about the current state of gender representation in peace and conflict studies remains limited. This study aims to investigate gender representation in peace and conflict studies by examining a newly collected dataset of articles published in five academic journals representative of the field between 2000 and 2024. We find that, although the gender gap has not disappeared yet, it has narrowed over time. Our results show that increased collaboration, particularly across genders, appears to be an important driver of this trend. Additionally, we find evidence that gender differences in topical specialization exist in the field and that a gender gap in citation patterns exists for some of the field&amp;rsquo;s core journals. Continued efforts are needed to further improve gender representation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legislative Politics under “One Country, Two Systems”: Evidence from Macau, 2013–2021</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-legislative-politics-under-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-legislative-politics-under-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legislative Politics under &#39;One Country, Two Systems&#39;: Evidence from Macau, 2013–2021</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the dynamics of legislative politics within the unique political context of the Macau Special Administrative Region (SAR) of China. Drawing on recently collected data from roll-call votes and committee deliberations taken during the fifth and sixth legislative assemblies, this study shifts the focus from electoral processes and resolution proposals to an analysis of bill proposals with the potential to become law. The findings reveal a structural dichotomy between a large, cohesive pro-establishment faction and a smaller, more fragmented opposition, which contrasts with the findings of previous research that suggest a more balanced opposition. Further analysis of committee deliberations indicates that this stable dichotomy allows regime loyalists to voice dissent without appearing rebellious, enabling ruling elites to gauge and respond to constituents’ preferences on non-sensitive issues. This dynamic highlights the distinct legislative practices of Macau SAR under the “one country, two systems” framework.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Daughters Change Their Fathers? Evidence from the First-Daughter Effect in Japan</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/daughter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/daughter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Family experiences—especially the gender of one’s children—can reshape parents’ political attitudes, challenging traditional models of political socialization. Studies in advanced democracies find that fathers of first-born daughters adopt more egalitarian views on gender roles, a phenomenon known as the first-daughter effect. Yet evidence from more conservative or non-Western contexts remains limited or inconclusive. This study examines whether the first-daughter effect holds in Japan, a country with stable democratic institutions but persistent gender inequality. Using nationally representative survey data from 2000 to 2018 and leveraging the quasi-random assignment of first-child sex, we find that Japanese fathers with first-born daughters exhibit significantly more gender-egalitarian attitudes and stronger support for related policy reforms, such as dual-surname legislation. These effects are specific to gender-related domains and do not extend to broader political ideology or non-gender-related policy preferences. Our findings contribute to research on reverse political socialization by demonstrating that the experience of raising daughters can shift core political attitudes, even in culturally conservative settings. This suggests that private, familial dynamics may serve as an underrecognized but powerful mechanism for promoting gender equality in public opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Central Authority and Local Interests: Insights from Macau&#39;s Gambling Law Amendment</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The balance between central authority and local interests has become a critical issue in recent studies of Chinese politics. This paper examines how local governments respond to conflict of interest with the central government, using Macau’s gambling law amendment as a case study. The findings suggest that under the “One Country, Two Systems” (OCTS) framework, the relationship between central and local authorities has been significantly redefined in recent years. Central directives now exert unprecedented influence over the governance of Hong Kong and Macau. At the same time, local interests persist but are increasingly confined to areas that do not directly challenge central policies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financial Crises and the Selection and Survival of Women Finance Ministers</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/armstrong-financial-crises-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/armstrong-financial-crises-2024/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Belief in Territorial Indivisibility and Public Preferences for Dispute Resolution</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/fang-belief-territorial-indivisibility-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/fang-belief-territorial-indivisibility-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Military Coalitions and Crisis Duration</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-military-coalitions-crisis-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-military-coalitions-crisis-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Legacy and Foreign Aid: Decomposing the Colonial Bias</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-colonial-legacy-foreign-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-colonial-legacy-foreign-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shape of Things to Come? Expanding the Inequality and Grievance Model for Civil War Forecasts with Event Data</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-shape-things-come-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-shape-things-come-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Careful Commitments: Democratic States and Alliance Design</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-careful-commitments-democratic-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-careful-commitments-democratic-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Story Has a Beginning, Middle, and an End (But Not Always in That Order): Predicting Duration Dynamics in a Unified Framework</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-every-story-has-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-every-story-has-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Copula Approach to the Problem of Selection Bias in Models of Government Survival</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-copula-approach-problem-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-copula-approach-problem-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major Powers and Militarized Conflict</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-major-powers-militarized-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-major-powers-militarized-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Institutional Opposition, Regime Accountability, and International Conflict</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-institutional-opposition-regime-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-institutional-opposition-regime-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing the Relationship Between Contiguity and Militarized Conflict</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/reed-decomposing-relationship-contiguity-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/reed-decomposing-relationship-contiguity-2010/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
