<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches | Daina Chiba</title>
    <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dainachiba.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Researches</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dainachiba.github.io/media/icon_hu2e8632b74444b790220bb01d3e17bdf2_10117_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Researches</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gender Gap in Peace and Conflict Journals, 2000-2024</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/genderpeaceconflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/genderpeaceconflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While the issue of gender representation has gained increasing recognition across various academic disciplines, existing knowledge about the current state of gender representation in peace and conflict studies remains limited. This study aims to investigate gender representation in peace and conflict studies by examining a newly collected dataset of articles published in five academic journals representative of the field between 2000 and 2024. We find that, although the gender gap has not disappeared yet, it has narrowed over time. Our results show that increased collaboration, particularly across genders, appears to be an important driver of this trend. Additionally, we find evidence that gender differences in topical specialization exist in the field and that a gender gap in citation patterns exists for some of the field&amp;rsquo;s core journals. Continued efforts are needed to further improve gender representation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Daughters Change Their Fathers? Evidence from the First-Daughter Effect in Japan</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/daughter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/daughter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Family experiences—especially the gender of one’s children—can reshape parents’ political attitudes, challenging traditional models of political socialization. Existing research in advanced democracies documents the “first-daughter effect,” whereby fathers of first-born daughters express more egalitarian views on gender roles. However, evidence from more conservative or non-Western contexts remains scarce and inconclusive. This study examines whether the first-daughter effect occurs in Japan, a country characterized by stable democratic institutions but enduring gender inequality. Using nationally representative survey data from 2000 to 2018 and leveraging the quasi-random assignment of first-child sex, we show that Japanese fathers with first-born daughters exhibit more gender-egalitarian attitudes. They also express greater support for gender-equality policy reforms, such as dual-surname legislation. These effects are confined to gender-related domains and do not extend to broader political ideology or non-gender-related policy preferences. Our findings contribute to research on reverse political socialization by demonstrating that raising daughters can reshape core political attitudes, even within culturally conservative settings. This suggests that private family dynamics may serve as an underrecognized but powerful mechanism for promoting gender equality in public opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Does it Mean to be a Reliable Ally?</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/alliance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/alliance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The value of military alliances is closely tied to whether alliance members will uphold their commitment if the treaty is invoked. Doubt about the reliability of an alliance can encourage aggression from rivals and, potentially, leave a state abandoned and fighting alone. Leveraging historical data on alliances and war, scholars have produced a variety of estimates of the reliability of alliances over time. We collect updated data on alliance reliability, highlighting some of the critical definitions and coding rules that impact assessments of reliability. We produce several different estimates of reliability at two levels of analysis (the alliance and the ally) using different data sources. We estimate that about two-thirds of the alliances invoked by war over a two-hundred year period were fulfilled, and about one-third violated. We note, however, that in the post-WWII period, alliance reliability, particularly among multilateral alliances, is lower than in prior eras. The lower estimate for multilateral alliance reliability after 1945 is driven by a small number of closely related cases, but still raises many questions for future research about potential changes in alliances and war that lead to different patterns in observed reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legislative Politics under &#39;One Country, Two Systems&#39;: Evidence from Macau, 2013–2021</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the dynamics of legislative politics within the unique political context of the Macau Special Administrative Region (SAR) of China. Drawing on recently collected data from roll-call votes and committee deliberations taken during the fifth and sixth legislative assemblies, this study shifts the focus from electoral processes and resolution proposals to an analysis of bill proposals with the potential to become law. The findings reveal a structural dichotomy between a large, cohesive pro-establishment faction and a smaller, more fragmented opposition, which contrasts with the findings of previous research that suggest a more balanced opposition. Further analysis of committee deliberations indicates that this stable dichotomy allows regime loyalists to voice dissent without appearing rebellious, enabling ruling elites to gauge and respond to constituents’ preferences on non-sensitive issues. This dynamic highlights the distinct legislative practices of Macau SAR under the “one country, two systems” framework.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Central Authority and Local Interests: Insights from Macau&#39;s Gambling Law Amendment</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The balance between central authority and local interests has become a critical issue in recent studies of Chinese politics. This paper examines how local governments respond to conflict of interest with the central government, using Macau’s gambling law amendment as a case study. The findings suggest that under the “One Country, Two Systems” (OCTS) framework, the relationship between central and local authorities has been significantly redefined in recent years. Central directives now exert unprecedented influence over the governance of Hong Kong and Macau. At the same time, local interests persist but are increasingly confined to areas that do not directly challenge central policies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make Two Democracies and Call Me in the Morning: Endogenous Regime Type and the Democratic Peace</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/make2dem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/make2dem/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
