<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conflict Forecast | Daina Chiba</title>
    <link>/tag/conflict-forecast/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/conflict-forecast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Conflict Forecast</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu2e8632b74444b790220bb01d3e17bdf2_10117_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Conflict Forecast</title>
      <link>/tag/conflict-forecast/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Much Ado about Something: Predicting Interstate Crises Onset and Resolution over Contentious Issues</title>
      <link>/research/muchado/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/muchado/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We explore whether dynamic information from event data can improve our
ability to forecast the onset and termination of international crises.
Studies of dyadic interstate conflicts have demonstrated that taking
into account contentious issues between countries can improve on
conventional models explaining dyadic violent conflict based on purely
structural factors (e.g., Gibler 2012, Gleditsch and Ward 2013).
However, data on contentious issues are often limited to particular
types such as claims over territory, river, or sea, although states
can experience violent conflict over various other issues such as
weapons program or regime type that may not be recorded in existing
data. Recent work on civil and interstate wars suggests that information
from news can improve structural conflict prediction that can help
capture changes over time (Chadefaux 2014, Muller &amp;amp; Rauh 2018). We seek to combine measures
of contentious issues and levels of conflict and cooperation between
states based on event data to forecast the onset and resolution of ICB
conflict data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shape of Things to Come? Expanding the Inequality and Grievance Model for Civil War Forecasts with Event Data</title>
      <link>/publication/chiba-shape-things-come-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/chiba-shape-things-come-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Story Has a Beginning, Middle, and an End (But Not Always in That Order): Predicting Duration Dynamics in a Unified Framework</title>
      <link>/publication/chiba-every-story-has-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/chiba-every-story-has-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
