<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jiying Jiang | Daina Chiba</title>
    <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/jiying-jiang/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/jiying-jiang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jiying Jiang</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dainachiba.github.io/media/icon_hu2e8632b74444b790220bb01d3e17bdf2_10117_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Jiying Jiang</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/authors/jiying-jiang/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legislative Politics under “One Country, Two Systems”: Evidence from Macau, 2013–2021</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-legislative-politics-under-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/publication/chiba-legislative-politics-under-2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legislative Politics under &#39;One Country, Two Systems&#39;: Evidence from Macau, 2013–2021</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/macaulegis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the dynamics of legislative politics within the unique political context of the Macau Special Administrative Region (SAR) of China. Drawing on recently collected data from roll-call votes and committee deliberations taken during the fifth and sixth legislative assemblies, this study shifts the focus from electoral processes and resolution proposals to an analysis of bill proposals with the potential to become law. The findings reveal a structural dichotomy between a large, cohesive pro-establishment faction and a smaller, more fragmented opposition, which contrasts with the findings of previous research that suggest a more balanced opposition. Further analysis of committee deliberations indicates that this stable dichotomy allows regime loyalists to voice dissent without appearing rebellious, enabling ruling elites to gauge and respond to constituents’ preferences on non-sensitive issues. This dynamic highlights the distinct legislative practices of Macau SAR under the “one country, two systems” framework.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Central Authority and Local Interests: Insights from Macau&#39;s Gambling Law Amendment</title>
      <link>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dainachiba.github.io/research/gamblinglaw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The balance between central authority and local interests has become a critical issue in recent studies of Chinese politics. This paper examines how local governments respond to conflict of interest with the central government, using Macau’s gambling law amendment as a case study. The findings suggest that under the “One Country, Two Systems” (OCTS) framework, the relationship between central and local authorities has been significantly redefined in recent years. Central directives now exert unprecedented influence over the governance of Hong Kong and Macau. At the same time, local interests persist but are increasingly confined to areas that do not directly challenge central policies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
